<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Maptastik!</title><link href="http://ryan-m-cooper.com/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://ryan-m-cooper.com/blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://ryan-m-cooper.com/blog/</id><updated>2018-01-14T16:56:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Remote GeoJSON to GeoDataFrame</title><link href="http://ryan-m-cooper.com/blog/remote-geojson-to-geodataframe.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-14T16:56:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-14T16:56:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Cooper</name></author><id>tag:ryan-m-cooper.com,2017-11-01:blog/remote-geojson-to-geodataframe.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Remote GeoJSON to GeoDataFrame&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m inspired by Stephen Smith’s quick post about rapid prototyping during his lunch break. Lately I’ve been using my lunch break to watch videos that are both related to the work I do for the City of Raleigh Park, Recreation &amp;amp; Cultural Resources Department and of interest to me. But sometimes I’d rather just mess around while I eat my turkey sandwich. I did just that today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re an Esri shop here at City of Raleigh, so most of my day-to-day is spent in that ecosystem. That said, I’ve been really interested in the Python library geopandas for a bit now and wanted to spend my lunch with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that’s great about geopandas is that you can read in all sorts of different data using gpd.read_file(). That’s great if you have a Shapefile or some GeoJSON on your machine. But what if you want to pull in some data from a URL? gpd.read_file() isn’t going to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So during lunch I messed around (e.g. Wrote some Python using Spyder, Googled things, ducked into Stack Overflow) and cobbled together a little function that takes a URL pointing to some GeoJSON as an input and returns a GeoDataFrame:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="gist"&gt;
    &lt;script src='https://gist.github.com/6030df87e8bd62fa583a83ecea9fceab.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;noscript&gt;
        &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;import requests, json, geopandas as gpd

def remoteGeoJSONToGDF(url, display = False):
    """Import remote GeoJSON to a GeoDataFrame
    Keyword arguments:
    url -- URL to GeoJSON resource on web
    display -- Displays geometries upon loading (default: False)
    """
    r = requests.get(url)
    data = r.json()
    gdf = gpd.GeoDataFrame.from_features(data['features'])
    if display:
        gdf.plot()
    return gdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="geopandas"></category><category term="geojson"></category><category term="Python Pandas"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry></feed>